<XML><RECORDS><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>47</REFNUM><YEAR>2005</YEAR><NOTES>TY  - JOUR</NOTES><TITLE>Peptidylarginine deiminase type 4, anticitrullinated peptide antibodies, and rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Autoimmunity Reviews</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>4</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><PAGES>201-206</PAGES><DATE>2005/4</DATE><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><URL>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6W8V-4F0829Y-1/2/afe9bc369b71e14ee65624b694060487</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>42</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><TITLE>Recent findings on genes associated with inflammatory disease</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs):Detection, Interpretation, and Application. Mutation Research - Fundamental and Molecular Mechanisms of Mutagenesis</SECONDARY_TITLE></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>41</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15574347</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>10</VOLUME><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>Jan 1</DATE><TITLE>Citrullinated proteins in rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><PAGES>54-64</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Citrullinated proteins that are produced by enzymatic deimination of arginine residues in proteins by peptidylarginine deiminases (PADIs) are of particular interest in the pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis (RA). First, peptidylarginine deiminase type 4 (PADI4) gene, which codes one of the PADI enzyme isotypes, has a genetic variant that increases susceptibility to RA. The RA-susceptible variant of PADI4 seems to increase the risk of RA by increasing its enzymatic activity. Second, this post-translational protein modification unfolds proteins by loss of a positive charge in arginine residues, with a subsequent change in antigenicity of the self-proteins. Third, these citrullinated proteins are recognized by anti-citrullinated peptide antibodies that are the most RA-specific autoantibodies. Finally, the expression of the PADI enzyme, citrullination of proteins, and production of anti-citrullinated protein antibodies occur in synovium. These data suggest that citrullination of proteins by PADI is related to alteration of antigenicity of peptides and very closely linked to pathogenesis of RA autoimmunity.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, Riken, Yokohama, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1093-4715&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Front Biosci</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15574347</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>48</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>16134727</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>34</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>May-Jun</DATE><TITLE>Peptidylarginine deiminase 4 (PADI4) identified as a conformation-dependent autoantigen in rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><PAGES>212-5</PAGES><ABSTRACT>OBJECTIVE: Peptidylarginine deiminase (PADI) catalyses the post-translational modification of arginine to citrulline, which is specifically recognized by sera from rheumatoid arthritis (RA) patients. The PADI4 gene has recently been identified as a risk factor for RA. We aimed to determine whether PADI4 constitutes an autoantigen in RA. METHODS: Serum samples were obtained from 42 patients with RA, 19 patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), 23 patients with other rheumatic diseases, and 40 normal individuals. The presence of antibodies against recombinant human PADI4 (anti-PADI4) was examined using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and Western blotting. RESULTS: For ELISA, the prevalence of anti-PADI4 among RA patients (50%) was significantly higher than that of normal individuals (2.5%), SLE (10.5%), and other rheumatic diseases (4.3%), while for Western blot analysis, PADI4 was recognized only by a portion of the ELISA-positive serum samples. CONCLUSIONS: PADI4 is an autoantigen in some RA patients, and its conformational epitope(s) may be important.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Department of Allergy and Rheumatology, University of Tokyo School of Medicine, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Takizawa, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Inoue, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0300-9742&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Scand J Rheumatol</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=16134727</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>40</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15629448</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>327</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>Feb 4</DATE><TITLE>Comparison of enzymatic properties between hPADI2 and hPADI4</TITLE><PAGES>192-200</PAGES><ABSTRACT>In the sera of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) patients, autoantibodies directed to citrullinated proteins are found with high specificity for RA. Peptidylarginine deiminases (PADIs) are enzymes responsible for protein citrullination. Among many isoforms of PADIs, only PADI4 has been identified as an RA-susceptibility gene. To understand the mechanisms of the initiation and progression of RA, we compared the properties of two PADIs, human PADI2 and human PADI4, which are present in the synovial tissues of RA patients. We confirmed their precise distribution in the RA synovium and compared the stability, Ca(2+) dependency, optimal pH range, and substrate specificity. Small but significant differences were found in the above-mentioned properties between hPADI2 and hPADI4. Using LC/MS/MS analysis, we identified the sequences in human fibrinogen indicating that hPADI2 and hPADI4 citrullinate in different manners. Our results indicate that hPADI2 and hPADI4 have different roles under physiological and pathological conditions. Further studies are needed for the better understanding of the role of hPADIs in the initiation and progression of RA.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Sankyo Co., Ltd., 1-2-58 Hiromachi, Shinagawa-ku, Tokyo 140-8710, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Nakayama-Hamada, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kubota, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takazawa, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohsaka, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kawaida, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ono, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kasuya, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Furukawa, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0006-291x&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15629448</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>43</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Mori, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kobayashi, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kawaida, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><TITLE>Ethnic differences in allele frequency of autoimmune disease-associated SNPs</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>46</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Kochi, Y</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Harley, JB</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Shirasawa, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Bae, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takahashi, A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kaufman, KM</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kang, CP</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kang, C</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Otsubo, S</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yumura, W</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mimori, A</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koike, T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sasazuki, T</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><TITLE>A functional variant in FCRL3, encoding Fc receptor-like 3, is associated with rheumatoid arthritis and several autoimmunities</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nat Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>37</VOLUME><NUMBER>5</NUMBER><PAGES>478-485</PAGES><DATE>2005/05//print</DATE><TYPE_OF_WORK>10.1038/ng1540</TYPE_OF_WORK><ALTERNATE_TITLE>Nat Genet</ALTERNATE_TITLE><ISBN>1061-4036</ISBN></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>37</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15466895</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>44</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><YEAR>2005</YEAR><DATE>Jan</DATE><TITLE>Localization of peptidylarginine deiminase 4 (PADI4) and citrullinated protein in synovial tissue of rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><PAGES>40-50</PAGES><ABSTRACT>OBJECTIVES: Peptidylarginine deiminases (PADIs) convert peptidylarginine into citrulline via post-translational modification. Anti-citrullinated peptide antibodies are highly specific for rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Our genome-wide case-control study of single-nucleotide polymorphisms found that the PADI4 gene polymorphism is closely associated with RA. Here, we localized the expression of PADI4 and the citrullinated protein product in synovial RA tissue. METHODS: We used immunohistochemistry, double immunofluorescent labelling and western blotting. RESULTS: We found that PADI4 is extensively expressed in T cells, B cells, macrophages, neutrophils, fibroblast-like cells and endothelial cells in the lining and sublining areas of the RA synovium. We also found extracellular and intracellular expression of PADI4 in fibrin deposits with loose tissue structures where apoptosis was widespread. Unlike PADI4, citrullinated protein generally appeared in fibrin deposits that were abundant in the RA synovium. The citrullinated fibrin aggregate was immunoreactive against immunoglobulin (Ig) A and IgM, but not IgG and IgE. Although a little PADI4 was expressed in osteoarthritic and normal synovial tissues, significant citrullination was undetectable. CONCLUSIONS: The results showed that PADI4 is mainly distributed in cells of various haematopoietic lineages and expressed at high levels in the inflamed RA synovium. The co-localization of PADI4, citrullinated protein and apoptotic cells in fibrin deposits suggests that PADI4 is responsible for fibrin citrullination and is involved in apoptosis. The immunoreactivity of citrullinated fibrin with IgA and IgM in the RA synovium supports the notion that citrullinated fibrin is a potential antigen of RA autoimmunity.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), 1-7-22 Suehiro, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa 230-0045, Japan. ryamada@src.riken.go.jp.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yoshino, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1462-0324&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Rheumatology (Oxford)</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15466895</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>36</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kochi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2005</YEAR><TITLE>The inhibition of antithrombin by peptidylarginine deiminase 4 may contribute to pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Rheumatology (Oxford)</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>44</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><PAGES>293-298</PAGES><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15561738</ACCESSION_NUMBER><ABSTRACT>Objective. The gene for peptidylarginine deiminase 4 (PADI4) has been found to be closely associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Peptidylarginine deiminase (PADI) catalyses the post-translational modification of peptidylarginine to citrulline, a reaction known as citrullination. PADI extracted from rabbit muscle has been reported to citrullinate antithrombin, a principal plasma inhibitor of thrombin. Thrombin is known to induce angiogenesis, fibrin formation and inflammation, the primary events of the RA joint. Here, we investigate whether human PADI4 can inhibit antithrombin by catalysing antithrombin citrullination and how the enzyme is involved in RA pathogenesis. Methods. Antithrombin was incubated with recombinant PADI4 protein, and the inactivation of antithrombin was determined by reduction of its thrombin-inhibiting activity. Citrullination of antithrombin was detected by western blotting and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). In addition, the citrullination level, activity and concentration of antithrombin in RA plasma were investigated by sandwich ELISA. Results. Incubation of antithrombin with PADI4 resulted in loss of thrombin-inhibitory activity and in citrullination of antithrombin. RA plasma showed higher levels of citrullinated antithrombin than controls with non-arthritis disease and healthy individuals. Conclusion. The results indicate that PADI4 could inactivate antithrombin through citrullination. The abnormal expression or activation of PADI4 in RA synovium is suggested to be responsible for the high level of citrullinated antithrombin in RA plasma. Local inhibition of antithrombin activity in RA synovium might lead to the excessive angiogenesis, fibrin deposition and inflammation of the tissue.</ABSTRACT><NOTES>1462-0324&#xD;Journal article</NOTES><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15561738</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>The Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN). 1-7-22 Suehiro, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa, 230-0045, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>31</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15184985</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>82</VOLUME><NUMBER>9</NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>Sep</DATE><TITLE>SLC22A4 and RUNX1: identification of RA susceptible genes</TITLE><PAGES>558-64</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Recently we reported that SLC22A4 and RUNX1 are associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). SLC22A4 is an organic cation transporter with unknown physiological function, and RUNX1 is a hematological transcriptional regulator that has been shown to be responsible for acute myelogenic leukemia. It is suggested that the association of RUNX1 with RA is due to its regulation of expression of SLC22A4. Because the physiological function of SLC22A4 is still unclear, further investigation is needed into how SLC22A4 affects RA susceptibility. Although the association of RUNX1 with RA was identified as a regulatory factor of SLC22A4, it is possible that RUNX1 is a key molecule in autoimmunity, as it has been reported to be associated with systemic lupus erythematosus and psoriasis, two other autoimmune diseases.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, Institute of Physical and Chemical Research, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, 230-0045, Yokohama, Kanagawa, Japan. ryamada@src.riken.go.jp</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0946-2716&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Mol Med</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15184985</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>26</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15184985</ACCESSION_NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>Jun 4</DATE><TITLE>SLC22A4 and RUNX1: identification of RA susceptible genes</TITLE><ABSTRACT>Recently we reported that SLC22A4 and RUNX1 are associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). SLC22A4 is an organic cation transporter with unknown physiological function, and RUNX1 is a hematological transcriptional regulator that has been shown to be responsible for acute myelogenic leukemia. It is suggested that the association of RUNX1 with RA is due to its regulation of expression of SLC22A4. Because the physiological function of SLC22A4 is still unclear, further investigation is needed into how SLC22A4 affects RA susceptibility. Although the association of RUNX1 with RA was identified as a regulatory factor of SLC22A4, it is possible that RUNX1 is a key molecule in autoimmunity, as it has been reported to be associated with systemic lupus erythematosus and psoriasis, two other autoimmune diseases.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, Institute of Physical and Chemical Research, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, 230-0045, Yokohama, Kanagawa, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0946-2716&#xD;Journal article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Mol Med</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15184985</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>25</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2004</YEAR><TITLE>CITRULLINATED PROTEINS IN RHEUMATOID ARTHRITIS</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Frontiers in BIoscience</SECONDARY_TITLE></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>27</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15190013</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>13</VOLUME><NUMBER>15</NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>Aug 1</DATE><TITLE>Variation of gene-based SNPs and linkage disequilibrium patterns in the human genome</TITLE><PAGES>1623-32</PAGES><ABSTRACT>A principal goal in human genetics is to provide the tools necessary to enable genome-wide association studies. Extensive information on the distribution of gene-based single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and linkage disequilibrium (LD) patterns across the genome is required in order to choose markers for efficient implementation of this approach. To obtain such information, we have genotyped a large Japanese cohort for SNPs identified by systematic resequencing of more than 14 000 autosomal genes. Analysis of these data led to the conclusion that the Japanese population contains approximately 130 000 common autosomal gene haplotypes (frequency &gt;0.05), of which more than 35% are identified in the present study. We also examined allele frequencies and LD patterns according to the position of variants within genes, and their distribution across the genome. We found lower allele variability at exonic SNP sites (both non-synonymous and synonymous) compared with non-exonic SNP sites, and greater average LD between SNPs within exons of the same gene compared with other SNP combinations, both of which could be signals of selection. LD was correlated with the recombination rate per physical distance as estimated from the meiotic map, but the strength of the relationship varied considerably in different regions of the genome. Unique LD patterns, characterized by frequent instances of high LD between non-adjacent SNPs punctuated by blocks of low LD, were found in a 7 Mb region on chromosome 6p that includes the MHC (major histocompatibility complex) locus and many non-MHC genes. These results demonstrate the complexity that must be taken into account when considering SNP variability and LD patterns, while also providing tools necessary for implementation of efficient genome-wide association studies.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Medical Informatics, SNP Research Center, RIKEN, Yokohama, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lathrop, G. M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takahashi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0964-6906&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Hum Mol Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15190013</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>28</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>14730600</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>50</VOLUME><NUMBER>1</NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>Jan</DATE><TITLE>Analysis of single-nucleotide polymorphisms in Japanese rheumatoid arthritis patients shows additional susceptibility markers besides the classic shared epitope susceptibility sequences</TITLE><PAGES>63-71</PAGES><ABSTRACT>OBJECTIVE: To examine the entire HLA region for loci (other than the DRB1 locus) associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) susceptibility, by typing HLA-DRB1 alleles and multiple single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the Japanese population. METHODS: The HLA-DRB1 alleles and 88 SNPs distributed over the HLA gene complex were genotyped, for 828 patients with RA and 1,032 control subjects. The data were evaluated for linkage disequilibrium, and case-control associations were analyzed in 2 ways, in the presence or absence of the disease-susceptibility DRB1 allele, to detect loci independent of the DRB1 allele. RESULTS: HLA-DRB1 alleles *0405, *0401, *0901, *0101, *1401, *1602, *0403, and *1405 were significantly associated with RA in the Japanese population. The smallest P value (P = 1.4 x 10(-27)) was observed in association with an intronic SNP of the NOTCH4 gene, which was due to strong linkage disequilibrium with the HLA-DRB1 allele. A strong association that was independent of HLA-DRB1 shared epitope alleles was observed in 2 SNPs: one in the intron of the MICA gene, the other in the intron of the HLA-DQB2 gene. Their association with RA, independent of HLA-DRB1 shared epitope alleles, was suggestive (P = 0.0024 [corrected P (P(corr)) = 0.068, and P = 0.00037 [P(corr) = 0.012], respectively). CONCLUSION: These findings suggest that 1 or more other loci besides the HLA-DRB1 or other DRB1 (non-shared epitope, non-*0901) alleles are involved in RA susceptibility/protection.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Kochi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kobayashi, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takahashi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mabuchi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Akiyama, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0004-3591&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Arthritis Rheum</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Adult</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Arthritis, Rheumatoid/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Epitopes/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Markers</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>HLA-DR Antigens/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Haplotypes</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=14730600</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>38</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15561738</ACCESSION_NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><DATE>Nov 23</DATE><TITLE>The inhibition of antithrombin by peptidylarginine deiminase 4 may contribute to pathogenesis of rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><ABSTRACT>Objective. The gene for peptidylarginine deiminase 4 (PADI4) has been found to be closely associated with rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Peptidylarginine deiminase (PADI) catalyses the post-translational modification of peptidylarginine to citrulline, a reaction known as citrullination. PADI extracted from rabbit muscle has been reported to citrullinate antithrombin, a principal plasma inhibitor of thrombin. Thrombin is known to induce angiogenesis, fibrin formation and inflammation, the primary events of the RA joint. Here, we investigate whether human PADI4 can inhibit antithrombin by catalysing antithrombin citrullination and how the enzyme is involved in RA pathogenesis. Methods. Antithrombin was incubated with recombinant PADI4 protein, and the inactivation of antithrombin was determined by reduction of its thrombin-inhibiting activity. Citrullination of antithrombin was detected by western blotting and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). In addition, the citrullination level, activity and concentration of antithrombin in RA plasma were investigated by sandwich ELISA. Results. Incubation of antithrombin with PADI4 resulted in loss of thrombin-inhibitory activity and in citrullination of antithrombin. RA plasma showed higher levels of citrullinated antithrombin than controls with non-arthritis disease and healthy individuals. Conclusion. The results indicate that PADI4 could inactivate antithrombin through citrullination. The abnormal expression or activation of PADI4 in RA synovium is suggested to be responsible for the high level of citrullinated antithrombin in RA plasma. Local inhibition of antithrombin activity in RA synovium might lead to the excessive angiogenesis, fibrin deposition and inflammation of the tissue.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>The Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN). 1-7-22 Suehiro, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa, 230-0045, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kochi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1462-0324&#xD;Journal article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Rheumatology (Oxford)</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15561738</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>35</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>15372322</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>49</VOLUME><NUMBER>10</NUMBER><YEAR>2004</YEAR><TITLE>Inference from the relationships between linkage disequilibrium and allele frequency distributions of 240 candidate SNPs in 109 drug-related genes in four Asian populations</TITLE><PAGES>558-72</PAGES><ABSTRACT>The extensive nucleotide diversity in drug-related genes predisposes individuals to different drug responses and is a major problem in current clinical practice and drug development. Striking allelic frequency differences exist in these genes between populations. In this study, we genotyped 240 sites known to be polymorphic in the Japanese population in each of 270 unrelated healthy individuals comprising 90 each of Malaysian Malays, Indians, and Chinese. These sites are distributed in 109 genes that are drug related, such as genes encoding drug-metabolizing enzymes and drug transporters. Allele frequency and linkage disequilibrium distributions of these sites were determined and compared. They were also compared with similar data of 752 Japanese. Extensive similarities in allele frequency and linkage disequilibrium distributions were observed among Japanese, Malaysian Chinese, and Malays. However, significant differences were observed between Japanese and Malaysian Chinese with Malaysian Indians. These four populations were grouped into two genetic clusters of different ancestries. However, a higher correlation was found between Malaysian Malays and Indians, indicating the existence of extensive admixture between them. The results also imply the possible and rational use of existing single nucleotide polymorphism databases as references to assist future pharmacogenetic studies involving populations of similar ancestry.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Institute of Biological Sciences (Genetics and Molecular Biology), Faculty of Science, University of Malaya, 50603, Lembah Pantai, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. genescha@yahoo.com.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Cha, P. C.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Koh, C. L.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1434-5161&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=15372322</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>33</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>14604829</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>9</VOLUME><NUMBER>11</NUMBER><YEAR>2003</YEAR><DATE>Nov</DATE><TITLE>Peptidylarginine deiminase type 4: identification of a rheumatoid arthritis-susceptible gene</TITLE><PAGES>503-8</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Recent studies using linkage disequilibrium and SNPs uncovered a rheumatoid arthritis (RA)-susceptible haplotype in the gene encoding peptidylarginine deiminase (PADI) type 4. This gene is one of four known PADI genes that encode enzymes to change arginine into citrulline in proteins. Post-translational modifications of proteins, including peptidyl citrullination, are related to autoimmunity, and peptidyl citrulline is a known target of one of the most RA-specific autoantibodies. Further research on PADI4, its citrullination of native peptides, subsequent breakdown of tolerance, and the role of these peptides in the development of RA, is expected to bring a better understanding of autoimmunity and arthritis, and advancements in the medical care of RA.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa, 230-0045, Japan. ryamada@src.riken.go.jp</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1471-4914&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Review&#xD;Review, Tutorial</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Trends Mol Med</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Animals</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Antibodies/immunology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Arthritis, Rheumatoid/enzymology/*genetics/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Autoimmunity/genetics/immunology/physiology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Citrulline/immunology/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Genetic Predisposition to Disease</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Hydrolases/*genetics/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Lymphocytes/immunology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Peptides/immunology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism (Genetics)</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=14604829</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>16</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kochi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagasaki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohtsuki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ono, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Furukawa, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagashima, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yoshino, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mabuchi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Saito, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takahashi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2003</YEAR><TITLE>An intronic SNP in a RUNX1 binding site of SLC22A4, encoding an organic cation transporter, is associated with rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nat Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>35</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><PAGES>341-348</PAGES><DATE>Nov 9</DATE><ACCESSION_NUMBER>14608356</ACCESSION_NUMBER><ABSTRACT>Rheumatoid arthritis is a common inflammatory disease with complex genetic components. We investigated the genetic contribution of the cytokine gene cluster in chromosome 5q31 to susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis in the Japanese population by case-control linkage disequilibrium (LD) mapping using single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). Here we report that there is significant association between rheumatoid arthritis and the organic cation transporter gene SLC22A4 (P = 0.000034). We show that expression of SLC22A4 is specific to hematological and immunological tissues and that SLC22A4 is also highly expressed in the inflammatory joints of mice with collagen-induced arthritis. A SNP affects the transcriptional efficiency of SLC22A4 in vitro, owing to an allelic difference in affinity to Runt-related transcription factor 1 (RUNX1), a transcriptional regulator in the hematopoietic system. A SNP in RUNX1 is also strongly associated with rheumatoid arthritis (P = 0.00035). Our data indicate that the regulation of SLC22A4 expression by RUNX1 is associated with susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis, which may represent an example of an epistatic effect of two genes on this disorder.</ABSTRACT><NOTES>1061-4036&#xD;Journal article</NOTES><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=14608356</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>[1] Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), 1-7-22, Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama City, Kanagawa 230-0045, Japan. [2] Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), 1-7-22, Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Sankyo, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>34</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12833157</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>34</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><YEAR>2003</YEAR><DATE>Aug</DATE><TITLE>Functional haplotypes of PADI4, encoding citrullinating enzyme peptidylarginine deiminase 4, are associated with rheumatoid arthritis</TITLE><PAGES>395-402</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Individuals with rheumatoid arthritis frequently have autoantibodies to citrullinated peptides, suggesting the involvement of the peptidylarginine deiminases citrullinating enzymes (encoded by PADI genes) in rheumatoid arthritis. Previous linkage studies have shown that a susceptibility locus for rheumatoid arthritis includes four PADI genes but did not establish which PADI gene confers susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis. We used a case-control linkage disequilibrium study to show that PADI type 4 is a susceptibility locus for rheumatoid arthritis (P = 0.000008). PADI4 was expressed in hematological and rheumatoid arthritis synovial tissues. We also identified a haplotype of PADI4 associated with susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis that affected stability of transcripts and was associated with levels of antibody to citrullinated peptide in sera from individuals with rheumatoid arthritis. Our results imply that the PADI4 haplotype associated with susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis increases production of citrullinated peptides acting as autoantigens, resulting in heightened risk of developing the disease.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), 1-7-22, Suehirocho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama City, Kanagawa 230-0045, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Suzuki, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Chang, X.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tokuhiro, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagasaki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakayama-Hamada, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kawaida, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ono, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohtsuki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Furukawa, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yoshino, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yukioka, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tohma, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Matsubara, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Wakitani, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Teshima, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nishioka, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Iida, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takahashi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1061-4036&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nat Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Adult</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Aged, 80 and over</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Arthritis, Rheumatoid/*enzymology/*genetics/immunology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Autoantibodies/blood</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Autoantigens/chemistry/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 1/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Citrulline/chemistry/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Haplotypes</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Hydrolases/*genetics/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Intermediate Filament Proteins/chemistry/immunology/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Peptides/chemistry/immunology/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>RNA Stability</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>RNA, Messenger/genetics/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12833157</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>11</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12740691</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>48</VOLUME><NUMBER>6</NUMBER><YEAR>2003</YEAR><TITLE>Association of single-nucleotide polymorphisms in the polymeric immunoglobulin receptor gene with immunoglobulin A nephropathy (IgAN) in Japanese patients</TITLE><PAGES>293-9</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Immunoglobulin A nephropathy (IgAN) is a primary glomerulonephritis of common incidence world-wide whose etiology and pathogenesis remain unresolved, although genetic factors are assumed to be involved in the development and progression of this disease. To identify genetic variations that might confer susceptibility to IgAN, we performed a case-control association study involving 389 Japanese IgAN patients and 465 controls. Genome-wide analysis of approximately 80,000 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) identified a significant association between IgAN and six SNPs located in the PIGR (polymeric immuoglobulin receptor) gene at chromosome 1q31-q41. One of them, PIGR-17, caused an amino-acid substitution from alanine to valine at codon 580 (chi(2)=13.05, P=0.0003, odds ratio [OR] =1.59, 95% confidence interval [95% CI] =1.24-2.05); the OR of minor homozygotes to others was 2.71 (95% CI=1.31-5.61). Another SNP, PIGR-2, could affect promoter activity (chi(2)=11.95, P=0.00055, OR=1.60, 95% CI=1.22-2.08); the OR of minor homozygotes to others was 2.08 (95% CI=0.94-4.60). Pairwise analyses demonstrated that all six SNPs were in almost complete linkage disequilibrium. Biopsy specimens from IgAN patients were positively stained by antibody against the secretory component of PIGR, but corresponding tissues from non-IgAN patients were not. Our results suggest that a gene associated with susceptibility to IgAN lies within or close to the PIGR gene locus on chromosome 1q in the Japanese population.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Human Genome Center, The Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Obara, W.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Iida, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Akiyama, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maeda, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takei, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ito, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Honda, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uchida, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsuchiya, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yumura, W.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ujiie, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagane, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nitta, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Miyano, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Narita, I.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gejyo, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nihei, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fujioka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1434-5161&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12740691</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>2</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>11828340</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>70</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><YEAR>2002</YEAR><DATE>Mar</DATE><TITLE>Association between single-nucleotide polymorphisms in selectin genes and immunoglobulin A nephropathy</TITLE><PAGES>781-6</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Although intensive efforts have been undertaken to elucidate the genetic background of immunoglobulin A nephropathy (IgAN), genetic factors associated with the pathogenesis of this disease are still not well understood. We designed a case-control association study that was based on linkage disequilibrium among single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the selectin gene cluster on chromosome 1q24-25, and we found two SNPs in the E-selectin gene (SELE8 and SELE13) and six SNPs in the L-selectin gene (SELL1, SELL4, SELL5, SELL6, SELL10, and SELL11) that were significantly associated with IgAN in Japanese patients. All eight SNPs were in almost complete linkage disequilibrium. SELE8 and SELL10 caused amino acid substitutions from His to Tyr and from Pro to Ser (chi2=9.02, P=.0026, odds ratio = 2.73 [95% confidence interval [CI] 1.38--5.38] for His-to-Tyr substitutions; chi2=17.4, P=.000031, odds ratio = 3.61 [95% CI 1.91--6.83] for Pro-to-Ser substitutions), and SELL1 could affect promoter activity of the L-selectin gene (chi2=19.5, P=.000010, odds ratio = 3.77 [95% CI 2.02--7.05]). The TGT haplotype at these three loci was associated significantly with IgAN (chi2=18.67, P=.000016, odds ratio = 1.88 [95% CI 1.41--2.51]). Our results suggest that these eight SNPs in selectin genes may be useful for screening populations susceptible to the IgAN phenotype that involves interstitial infiltration.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Human Genome Center, The Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Tokyo Women&apos;s Medical University, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Takei, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Iida, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nitta, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maeda, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takeoka, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ito, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Honda, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uchida, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsuchiya, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fujioka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ujiie, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagane, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Miyano, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Narita, I.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gejyo, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nihei, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0002-9297&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Am J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 1/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>E-Selectin/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Screening</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Glomerulonephritis, IGA/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Haplotypes/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>L-Selectin/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Multigene Family/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Odds Ratio</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Promoter Regions (Genetics)/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=11828340</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>4</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12426569</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>32</VOLUME><NUMBER>4</NUMBER><YEAR>2002</YEAR><DATE>Dec</DATE><TITLE>Functional SNPs in the lymphotoxin-alpha gene that are associated with susceptibility to myocardial infarction</TITLE><PAGES>650-4</PAGES><ABSTRACT>By means of a large-scale, case-control association study using 92,788 gene-based single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers, we identified a candidate locus on chromosome 6p21 associated with susceptibility to myocardial infarction. Subsequent linkage-disequilibrium (LD) mapping and analyses of haplotype structure showed significant associations between myocardial infarction and a single 50 kb halpotype comprised of five SNPs in LTA (encoding lymphotoxin-alpha), NFKBIL1 (encoding nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in B cells, inhibitor-like 1) and BAT1 (encoding HLA-B associated transcript 1). Homozygosity with respect to each of the two SNPs in LTA was significantly associated with increased risk for myocardial infarction (odds ratio = 1.78, chi(2) = 21.6, P = 0.00000033; 1,133 affected individuals versus 1,006 controls). In vitro functional analyses indicated that one SNP in the coding region of LTA, which changed an amino-acid residue from threonine to asparagine (Thr26Asn), effected a twofold increase in induction of several cell-adhesion molecules, including VCAM1, in vascular smooth-muscle cells of human coronary artery. Moreover, the SNP, in intron 1 of LTA, enhanced the transcriptional level of LTA. These results indicate that variants in the LTA are risk factors for myocardial infraction and implicate LTA in the pathogenesis of the disorder.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Cardiovascular Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), 4-6-1, Shirokanedai, Minato-ku, Tokyo 108-8639, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Ozaki, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Iida, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sekine, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sato, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hori, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1061-4036&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Nat Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Amino Acid Substitution</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Cells, Cultured</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Chromosome Mapping</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 6</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Coronary Vessels/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Databases, Genetic</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Gene Frequency</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Genetic Predisposition to Disease</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Screening</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Haplotypes</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Homozygote</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Introns</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Jurkat Cells</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Lymphotoxin/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Age</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Muscle, Smooth, Vascular/cytology/physiology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Myocardial Infarction/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Recombinant Fusion Proteins/metabolism</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Sequence Analysis, DNA</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Transcription, Genetic</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Vascular Cell Adhesion Molecule-1/biosynthesis</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12426569</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>13</REFNUM><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Ikeda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Mabuchi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fukuda, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kawakami, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Miyoshi, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Haga, N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hiraoka, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takatori, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kawaguchi, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ikegawa, S.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><YEAR>2002</YEAR><TITLE>Association analysis of single nucleotide polymorphisms in cartilage-specific collagen genes with knee and hip osteoarthritis in the Japanese population</TITLE><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Bone Miner Res</SECONDARY_TITLE><VOLUME>17</VOLUME><NUMBER>7</NUMBER><PAGES>1290-6</PAGES><DATE>Jul</DATE><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12096843</ACCESSION_NUMBER><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Cartilage, Articular</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Collagen Type II/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Collagen Type IX/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Collagen Type X/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Collagen Type XI/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Haplotypes</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Age</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Osteoarthritis, Hip/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Osteoarthritis, Knee/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><ABSTRACT>Osteoarthritis (OA) is one of the most common diseases in the elderly. Although its pathophysiology is complex and its molecular basis remains to be determined, much evidence suggests that OA has strong genetic determinants. To search for susceptibility loci of OA, we selected seven candidate genes encoding cartilage-specific collagens (type II, IX, X, and XI collagens) and performed association analysis for OA using single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the coding region of these genes. Four hundred seventeen OA samples and 280 control samples were collected from the Japanese population, and 12 SNPs were genotyped. Our studies have identified two susceptibility loci of OA: COL2A1 and COL9A3. An SNP in COL9A3 showed significant association with knee OA (p = 0.002, odds ratio [OR] = 1.48). Haplotype analysis showed significant association between a specific haplotype of COL2A1 and hip OA (p = 0.024; OR = 1.30). Further analysis of these two genes will shed light on the molecular mechanisms of OA.</ABSTRACT><NOTES>0884-0431&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12096843</URL><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Bone and Joint Diseases, SNP Research Center, RIKEN (The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research), Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>5</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12436197</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>47</VOLUME><NUMBER>11</NUMBER><YEAR>2002</YEAR><TITLE>Gene-based SNP discovery as part of the Japanese Millennium Genome Project: identification of 190,562 genetic variations in the human genome. Single-nucleotide polymorphism</TITLE><PAGES>605-10</PAGES><ABSTRACT>To construct an infrastructure for genome-wide association studies of common diseases or drug sensitivities, we have been systematically exploring common variants by resequencing genomic regions containing genes in DNA from 24 Japanese individuals. We have analyzed a total of 154 Mb, corresponding to approximately 5% of the human genome, and so far have identified 174,269 single-nucleotide polymorphisms and 16,293 insertion/deletion polymorphisms within gene regions, i.e., one polymorphism in 807 bp on average. Our data are freely available via our web site (http://snp.ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp) and will facilitate studies to identify genes associated with susceptibility to common diseases and genes involved in sensitivity to therapeutic drugs.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory of Molecular Medicine, Human Genome Center, Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Haga, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1434-5161&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Gene Frequency</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Genome, Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human Genome Project</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymerase Chain Reaction</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Variation (Genetics)</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12436197</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>10</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>12376743</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>47</VOLUME><NUMBER>10</NUMBER><YEAR>2002</YEAR><TITLE>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms in the class II region of the major histocompatibility complex in Japanese patients with immunoglobulin A nephropathy</TITLE><PAGES>532-8</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Immunoglobulin A nephropathy (IgAN) is a form of chronic glomerulonephritis of unknown etiology and pathogenesis. Immunogenetic studies have not conclusively indicated that human leukocyte antigen (HLA) is involved. As a first step in investigating a possible relationship between HLA class II genes and IgAN, we analyzed the extent of linkage disequilibrium (LD) in this region of chromosome 6p21.3 in a Japanese test population and found extended LD blocks within the class II locus. We designed a case-control association study of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in each of those LD blocks, and determined that SNPs located in the HLA- DRA gene were significantly associated with an increased risk of IgAN ( P = 0.000001, odds ratio = 1.91 [95% confidence interval 1.46-2.49]); SNPs in other LD blocks were not. Our data imply that some haplotype of the HLA- DRA locus has an important role in the development of IgAN in Japanese patients.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Human Genome Center, The Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Akiyama, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maeda, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takei, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Obara, W.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ito, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Honda, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Uchida, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsuchiya, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nitta, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yumura, W.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nihei, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ujiie, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagane, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Miyano, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fujioka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Narita, I.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Gejyo, F.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1434-5161&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Adult</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Alleles</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Chromosomes, Human, Pair 6/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Comparative Study</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genes, MHC Class II/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Predisposition to Disease</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Glomerulonephritis, IGA/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>HLA-DR Antigens/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Linkage Disequilibrium/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Age</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Odds Ratio</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=12376743</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>1</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>11179015</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>68</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><YEAR>2001</YEAR><DATE>Mar</DATE><TITLE>Association between a single-nucleotide polymorphism in the promoter of the human interleukin-3 gene and rheumatoid arthritis in Japanese patients, and maximum-likelihood estimation of combinatorial effect that two genetic loci have on susceptibility to the disease</TITLE><PAGES>674-85</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Genetic variants of interleukin-3 (IL-3), a well-studied cytokine, may have a role in the pathophysiology of rheumatoid arthritis (RA); but reports on this association sometimes conflict. A case-control study was designed to investigate association between RA and a single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in the IL-3 promoter region. Comparison of cases of RA versus control individuals yielded a chi(2) value of 14.28 (P=.0002), with a genotype odds ratio of 2.24 (95% confidence interval [95%CI] 1.44-3.49). When female cases with earlier onset were compared with female control individuals, the SNP revealed an even more significant correlation, with chi2=21.75 (P=.000004) and a genotype odds ratio of 7.27 (95%CI 2.80-18.89). The stronger association that we observed in this clinically distinct subgroup (females with early onset), within a region where linkage disequilibrium was not significantly extended, suggested that the genuine RA locus should locate either within or close to the IL-3 gene. Combined genotype data on SNPs on eight other candidate genes were combined with our IL-3 results, to estimate relationships between pairs of loci and RA, by maximum-likelihood analysis. The utility of combining the genotype data in this way to identify possible contributions of various genes to this disease is discussed.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory of Rheumatic Diseases, SNP Research Center, Institute of Physical and Chemical Research, Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Unoki, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagai, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sawada, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yukioka, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maeda, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tateishi, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ochi, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0002-9297&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Am J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Age of Onset</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Arthritis, Rheumatoid/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Comparative Study</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Predisposition to Disease/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>HLA-DR Antigens/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Interleukin-3/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Likelihood Functions</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Middle Age</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Models, Statistical</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Molecular Sequence Data</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Mongoloid Race/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Odds Ratio</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Promoter Regions (Genetics)</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Reference Values</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=11179015</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>6</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>11501945</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>46</VOLUME><NUMBER>8</NUMBER><YEAR>2001</YEAR><TITLE>A high-throughput SNP typing system for genome-wide association studies</TITLE><PAGES>471-7</PAGES><ABSTRACT>One of the most difficult issues to be solved in genome-wide association studies is to reduce the amount of genomic DNA required for genotyping. Currently available technologies require too large a quantity of genomic DNA to genotype with hundreds or thousands of single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). To overcome this problem, we combined the Invader assay with multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR), carried out in the presence of antibody to Taq polymerase, as well as using a novel 384-well card system that can reduce the required reaction volume. We amplified 100 genomic DNA fragments, each containing one SNP, in a single tube, and analyzed each SNP with the Invader assay. This procedure correctly genotyped 98 of the 100 SNP loci examined in PCR-amplified samples from ten individuals: the genotypes were confirmed by direct sequencing. The reproducibility and universality of the method were confirmed with two additional sets of 100 SNPs. Because we used 40 ng of genomic DNA as a template for multiplex PCR, the amount needed to assay one SNP was only 0.4 ng; therefore, theoretically, more than 200,000 SNPs could be genotyped at once when 100 microg of genomic DNA is available. Our results indicate the feasibility of undertaking genome-wide association studies using blood samples of only 5-10 ml.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory for Cardiovascular Diseases, SNP Research Center, The Institute of Physical and Chemical Research (RIKEN), Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ozaki, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suzuki, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>1434-5161&#xD;Evaluation Studies&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Alleles</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Energy Transfer/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Fluorescent Dyes/analysis</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Gene Amplification</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genetic Markers</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Genome, Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymerase Chain Reaction/economics/instrumentation/*methods</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Reproducibility of Results</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Support, Non-U.S. Gov&apos;t</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Taq Polymerase/metabolism</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=11501945</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>7</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>10798357</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>106</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><YEAR>2000</YEAR><DATE>Mar</DATE><TITLE>Identification of 142 single nucleotide polymorphisms in 41 candidate genes for rheumatoid arthritis in the Japanese population</TITLE><PAGES>293-7</PAGES><ABSTRACT>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) can make an important contribution to our understanding of genetic backgrounds that may influence medical conditions and ethnic diversity. We undertook a systematic survey of genomic DNA for SNPs located not only in coding sequences but also in non-coding regions (e.g., introns and 5&apos; flanking regions) of selected genes. Using DNA samples from 48 Japanese patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) as templates, we surveyed 41 genes that represent candidates for RA, screening a total of 104 kb of DNA (30 kb of coding sequences and 74 kb of non-coding DNA). Within this 104 kb of genomic sequences we identified 163 polymorphisms (1 per 638 bases on average), of which 142 were single-nucleotide substitutions and the remainder, insertions or deletions. Of the coding SNPs, 52% were non-synonymous substitutions, and non-conservative amino acid changes were observed in a quarter of those. Sixty-nine polymorphisms showed high frequencies for minor alleles (more than 15%) and 20 revealed low frequencies (&lt;5%). Our results indicated a greater average distance between SNPs than others have reported, but this disparity may reflect the type of genes surveyed and/or the relative ethnic homogeneity of our test population.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory of Molecular Medicine, Human Genome Center, Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suematsu, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Minami, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Seki, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yukioka, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Maeda, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Murata, N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Saiki, O.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Teshima, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kudo, O.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ishikawa, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ueyosi, A.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tateishi, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Inaba, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goto, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nishizawa, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tohma, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ochi, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamamoto, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0340-6717&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Alleles</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Arthritis, Rheumatoid/epidemiology/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Gene Frequency</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan/epidemiology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Proteins/genetics</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=10798357</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>3</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>11700591</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>11</VOLUME><YEAR>2000</YEAR><TITLE>Environmental factor dependent maximum likelihood method for association study targeted to personalized medicine</TITLE><PAGES>96-105</PAGES><ABSTRACT>The most challenging strategy for analyzing genome-wide polymorphisms and/or expression profiles is to solve multi-factor causal-relationship simultaneously. As the first step, we propose a framework of association study using maximum likelihood method that simultaneously handles genetic polymorphisms and epi-genetic information, e.g. environmental factors. We evaluate the theory by applying it to genotyped data of myocardial infarction (MI) patients.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>SNP Research Center, Institute of Chemical and Physical Research (RIKEN), Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, 4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato, Tokyo 108-8639, Japan. tatsu@ims.u-tokyo.ac.jp</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Tsunoda, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kamatani, N.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0919-9454&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Genome Inform Ser Workshop Genome Inform</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>Algorithms</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Case-Control Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Computational Biology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Environment</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Gene Expression Profiling</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Genotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Likelihood Functions</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Models, Genetic</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Myocardial Infarction/etiology/genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Phenotype</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Polymorphism (Genetics)</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Risk Factors</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=11700591</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>8</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>10798356</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>106</VOLUME><NUMBER>3</NUMBER><YEAR>2000</YEAR><DATE>Mar</DATE><TITLE>Identification of 187 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) among 41 candidate genes for ischemic heart disease in the Japanese population</TITLE><PAGES>288-92</PAGES><ABSTRACT>To investigate whether common variants in the human genetic background are associated with pathogenesis of ischemic heart diseases, we systematically surveyed 41 possible candidate genes for single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) by directly sequencing 96 independent alleles at each locus, derived from 48 unrelated Japanese patients with myocardial infarction, including 25.8 kb 5&apos; flanking regions, 56.8 kb exonic and 35.4 kb intronic sequences, and 1.8 kb 3&apos; flanking regions. In this genomic DNA of nearly 120 kb, we identified 187 SNPs: 55 in 5&apos; flanking regions, seven in 5&apos; untranslated regions (UTRs), 52 in coding elements, 64 in introns, eight in 3&apos; UTRs, and one in a 3&apos; flanking region. Among the 52 coding SNPs, 26 were non-synonymous changes. Allelic frequencies of some of the polymorphisms were significantly different from those reported in European populations. For example, the Q506R substitution in the coagulation factor V gene, the so-called &quot;Leiden mutation&quot;, has a reported frequency of 2.3% in Europeans, but we detected the Leiden mutation in none of the Japanese genomes that we investigated. The allelic frequencies of the -33A&gt;G SNP in the thrombomodulin gene were also very different; this allele occurred at a 12% frequency in the Japanese patients that we examined, although it had been detected in none of 82 Caucasians reported previously. These data support the hypothesis that some SNPs are specific to particular ethnic groups.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Laboratory of Molecular Medicine, Human Genome Center, Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, Japan.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Ohnishi, Y.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Tanaka, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Suematsu, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Minami, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Fujii, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hoki, N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kodama, K.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nagata, S.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hayashi, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kinoshita, N.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sato, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Kuzuya, T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Takeda, H.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hori, M.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Nakamura, Y.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0340-6717&#xD;Journal Article</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>Hum Genet</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>3&apos; Untranslated Regions</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>5&apos; Untranslated Regions</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Alleles</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Exons</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Introns</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Japan/epidemiology</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Myocardial Ischemia/epidemiology/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide/*genetics</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Proteins/genetics</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=10798356</URL></RECORD><RECORD><REFERENCE_TYPE>0</REFERENCE_TYPE><REFNUM>9</REFNUM><ACCESSION_NUMBER>10491246</ACCESSION_NUMBER><VOLUME>14</VOLUME><NUMBER>9</NUMBER><YEAR>1999</YEAR><DATE>Sep</DATE><TITLE>A multimedia intervention on cardiopulmonary resuscitation and advance directives</TITLE><PAGES>559-63</PAGES><ABSTRACT>OBJECTIVE: To assess the effects of a multimedia educational intervention about advance directives (ADs) and cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) on the knowledge, attitude and activity toward ADs and life-sustaining treatments of elderly veterans. DESIGN: Prospective randomized controlled, single blind study of educational interventions. SETTING: General medicine clinic of a university-affiliated Veterans Affairs Medical Center (VAMC). PARTICIPANTS: One hundred seventeen Veterans, 70 years of age or older, deemed able to make medical care decisions. INTERVENTION: The control group (n = 55) received a handout about ADs in use at the VAMC. The experimental group (n = 62) received the same handout, with an additional handout describing procedural aspects and outcomes of CPR, and they watched a videotape about ADs. MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS: Patients&apos; attitudes and actions toward ADs, CPR and life-sustaining treatments were recorded before the intervention, after it, and 2 to 4 weeks after the intervention through self-administered questionnaires. Only 27.8% of subjects stated that they knew what an AD is in the preintervention questionnaire. This proportion improved in both the experimental and control (87.2% experimental, 52.5% control) subject groups, but stated knowledge of what an AD is was higher in the experimental group (odds ratio = 6.18, p &lt;.001) and this effect, although diminished, persisted in the follow-up questionnaire (OR = 3.92, p =. 003). Prior to any intervention, 15% of subjects correctly estimated the likelihood of survival after CPR. This improved after the intervention in the experimental group (OR = 4.27, p =.004), but did not persist at follow-up. In the postintervention questionnaire, few subjects in either group stated that they discussed CPR or ADs with their physician on that day (OR = 0.97, p = NS). CONCLUSION: We developed a convenient means of educating elderly male patients regarding CPR and advance directives that improved short-term knowledge but did not stimulate advance care planning.</ABSTRACT><AUTHOR_ADDRESS>Department of Internal Medicine, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA.</AUTHOR_ADDRESS><AUTHORS><AUTHOR>Yamada, R.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Galecki, A. T.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Goold, S. D.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hogikyan, R. V.</AUTHOR></AUTHORS><NOTES>0884-8734&#xD;Clinical Trial&#xD;Journal Article&#xD;Randomized Controlled Trial</NOTES><SECONDARY_TITLE>J Gen Intern Med</SECONDARY_TITLE><KEYWORDS><KEYWORD>*Advance Directives</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Aged</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Aged, 80 and over</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation/*education</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Female</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Human</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Knowledge, Attitudes, Practice</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Male</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>*Multimedia</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Patient Education/*methods</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Prospective Studies</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Questionnaires</KEYWORD><KEYWORD>Single-Blind Method</KEYWORD></KEYWORDS><URL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Citation&amp;list_uids=10491246</URL></RECORD></RECORDS></XML>